Guide to the Victor S. Navasky Papers TAM.594
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series VII: Other Navasky Writings, 1930s-2012
  - Subseries VIIB: Articles and Essays
    - Articles: "Robert Kennedy--As Attorney General and His Father's Son: The Strange, Sad Tale of James Landis" (The Washington Post/Potomac Oct 3. 1971) (Box 71, Folder 3)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" (Esquire Apr 1987) (Box 68, Folder 20)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - correspondence, 1986 (Box 68, Folder 21)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - notebooks, undated (Box 68, Folder 22)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - notes, undated (Box 68, Folder 23)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - research, Attorney General Ed Meese, 1981-1986 (Box 68, Folder 24)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - research, civil rights, 1985-1986 (Box 68, Folder 25)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - research, civil rights - material focused on opposition to William Reinquist nomination, 1986 (Box 68, Folder 26)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - research, civil rights - "An Oath Betrayed: The Reagan Administration's Civil Rights Enforcement Record in Education", Oct 1983 (Box 68, Folder 27)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - research, civil rights - "Without Justice: A Report on the Conduct of the Justice Department in Civil Rights in 1981-1982", Feb 1982 (Box 68, Folder 28)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - research, Confronting Moscow (Heritage Foundation), 1985 (Box 68, Folder 29)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, "Draft Report on Antonin Scalia", 1986 (Box 69, Folder 1)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, "How's Business in the Reagan Era?...", Dec 1983 (Box 69, Folder 2)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, "Ideological Shaping of the Court" (articles), 1957, 1983-1986 (Box 69, Folder 3)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, "The Impact of Reagan Administration Policies on Regional Income and Employment", May 1986 (Box 69, Folder 4)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, "Impact of the Reagan Years on the Distribution of Income of the Elderly", Feb 1985 (Box 69, Folder 5)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, "Index to Clippings of Alleged Ethics Violations by Reagan Administration Appointees" compiled by Rep. Patricia Schroeder, Oct 23, 1986 (Box 69, Folder 6)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, Information and Disinformation, 1985-1986 (Box 69, Folder 7)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, "Interest Groups and Interest in the Reagan Era", Sep 1983 (Box 69, Folder 8)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, Judicial Nominations, 1985-1986 (Box 69, Folder 9)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, Newspaper Clippings, 1984-1987 (Box 69, Folder 10)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, Nicaragua, 1986 (Box 69, Folder 11)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, Perspectives on the Reagan Years edited by John L. Palmer, 1986 (Box 69, Folder 12)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, Policy Review (Heritage Foundation) 3 issues, 1986 (Box 69, Folder 13)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, "President Reagan and the Federal Budget...", Mar 1985 (Box 69, Folder 14)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, Potential nomination of Orrin Hatach to the US Supreme Court, 1986 (Box 69, Folder 15)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, "The Reagan Administration and the Social Safety Net for the Nonaged Poor", Dec 1983 (Box 69, Folder 16)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, "The Reagan Legacy" by Bernard Weinraub, Jun 22, 1986 (Box 71, Folder 4)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, "Ronald Reagan: Prisoner of his Own Dreams" by David Hoffman, Nov 1986 (Box 69, Folder 17)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, Publications ("Multinational Monitor", "People and Taxes", "The Defense Monitor"), 1985-1986 (Box 69, Folder 18)
    - Articles: "Ronald Reagan and the Supremes" - Research, Various items, 1984-1986 (Box 69, Folder 19)
    - Articles: "Saving The Nation" (Atlantic Monthly, Jan 1998) - includes article and draft, 1997-1998 (Box 69, Folder 20)
    - Articles: "Saving The Nation" - reader responses to article, 1997-1998 (Box 69, Folder 21)
    - Articles: "Stamp Out Bad Communications" (The Plain Dealer), Oct 1, 1991 (Box 69, Folder 22)
    - Articles: Unidentified article focused on future of book publishing and conglomerates (also mentions electronic books, etc) - background/research, 1980, undated (Box 69, Folder 23)
    - Articles: Unidentified article focused on future of book publishing and conglomerates (also mentions electronic books, etc) - draft fragments and notes, 1980, undated (Box 69, Folder 24)
    - Articles: Unidentified article focused on future of magazines, undated (Box 69, Folder 25)
    - Articles: Untitled draft of article concerning New York Times' failure to attribute "scoop" to The Nation, 2004 (Box 69, Folder 26)
    - Articles: Various, from The Nation, 1975-1985 (Box 69, Folder 27)
    - Articles: Various, from The Nation, 1990-2005, undated (Box 69, Folder 28)
    - Bittman, William: "Article In Progress" and related materials (includes Bittman FBI files), 1981 (Box 69, Folder 29)
    - Book Reviews, 1963-1999 (Box 69, Folder 30)
    - Book Reviews: The Big Foundations by Waldemar A. Nielsen (includes drafts, notes, correspondence), 1973 (Box 69, Folder 31)
    - Book Reviews: Fair Enough: The Life of Westbrook Pegler (includes related material), 1975 (Box 70, Folder 1)
    - Book Reviews: New York Times, 1971-1977, 1982, 2000 (Box 70, Folder 2)
    - Book Reviews: "The Ordeal of Meyer Levin" (includes article, correspondence and notes; also "Fifty Years in Writing" by Meyer Levin), 1973-1974 (Box 70, Folder 3)
    - Book Reviews: "The Ordeal of Meyer Levin" - annotated copy of The Obsession, 1973 (Box 70, Folder 4)
    - Book Reviews: "The Ordeal of Meyer Levin" - Plays in dispute (Anne Frank by Levin and The Diary of Anne Frank by the Hacketts), [1952], 1956 (Box 70, Folder 5)
    - Book Reviews: "Orphans of the Cold War" review of We Are Your Sons by Michael and Robert Meeropol, 1975 (Box 70, Folder 6)
    - Book Reviews: The Publish-It-Yourself Handbook, undated (Box 70, Folder 7)
    - Book Reviews: re: Navasky's review of Halberstam's The Best and the Brightest, 1973 (Box 70, Folder 8)
    - Book Reviews: "The Selling of the Brethren" The Yale Law Journal, Apr 1980 (Box 70, Folder 9)
    - Book Reviews: "The Selling of the Brethren" The Yale Law Journal (galleys), 1979-1980 (Box 70, Folder 10)
    - Contracts, 1954-1997 (Box 70, Folder 11)
    - Essay, "The Nation", for The Companion to American Thought, 1993 (Box 70, Folder 12)
    - "In Cold Print..." columns (The New York Times Book Review), Feb 1973-Apr 1974 (Box 70, Folder 13)
    - "In Cold Print..." columns (The New York Times Book Review), 1975 (Box 70, Folder 14)
    - "In Cold Print..." columns: notes, 1975 (Box 70, Folder 15)
    - "In Cold Print..." columns: research materials (includes Confrontation Fall 1974 containing articles on copyright), 1974-1975 (Box 70, Folder 16)
    - "In Cold Print": Coop publishing and other ideas (for columns), 1973-1974 (Box 70, Folder 17)
    - "In Cold Print": Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 70, Folder 18)
    - "In Cold Print": Correspondence, 1974-1975, undated (Box 70, Folder 19)
    - "In Cold Print: A Crime Writers' Mafia" (Jun 15, 1975) - article, correspondence, background material (Box 70, Folder 20)
    - "In Cold Print: A Crime Writers' Mafia" (Jun 15, 1975) - drafts and notes (Box 70, Folder 21)
    - "In Cold Print: Safe Publishing" (Mar 16, 1975): article, correspondence, fragments, notes (Box 70, Folder 22)
    - "In Cold Print: Safe Publishing" (Mar 16, 1975): Research, 1972-1974 (Box 70, Folder 23)
    - "In Cold Print: Safe Publishing" (Mar 16, 1975): Research, 1973-1974 (Box 70, Folder 24)
    - "In Cold Print: The Search for Subsidy": article, drafts, notes and related material, 1957-1958, 1975-1976 (Box 70, Folder 25)
    - "In Cold Print": Various columns - notes, undated (Box 70, Folder 26)
    - "In Cold Print: What is a Good Editor Worth?", 1972-1973 (Box 70, Folder 27)
    - "In Cold Print: What is a Good Editor Worth?" - Notes, 1973 (Box 72, Folder 1, Box 70, Folder 28)
    - "In Cold Print: Writers and Underwriters": article and related material, 1973 (Box 72, Folder 2)
    - "In Cold Print: Writers and Underwriters": drafts and notes, undated (Box 72, Folder 3)
    - Letters to the Editor, 1951, 1976, 1995 (Box 72, Folder 4)
    - Letters to the Editor: Civil Liberties Review "Ramsey Clark and Wiretapping", 1976 (Box 72, Folder 5)
    - What Orwell Didn't Know (Navasky a contributor): material related to appearance at Miami Book Fair, 2007 (Box 72, Folder 6)
  - Subseries VIIC: Articles and Essays - Alger Hiss
    The amount of material associated with Navasky's Alger Hiss-related articles warrants its own subseries, although much of it is focused on a single piece - "The Case not Proved Against Alger Hiss." The article is a critique of Allen Weinstein's 1978 book, Perjury: the Hiss-Chambers Case. Navasky conducted extensive research and interviews in preparation for the article, which appeared in the April 8, 1978, issue of The Nation. Not only does this subseries contain material associated with the article's research and writing, it also includes relevant items subsequent to its publication. An example involves Sam Kreiger, one of the individuals interviewed by both Weinstein and Navasky, who brought a libel suit against Weinstein in 1979. There are documents from Krieger, Sam v. Allen Weinstein et al. which include Weinstein's deposition and a transcript of Weinstein's interview of Kreiger.
    Navasky continued his criticism of Weinstein's work in a 1982 essay "Weinstein, Hiss, and the Transformation of Historical Ambiguity into Cold War Verity," which is included in a 1982 book edited by Athan G. Theoharis titled Beyond the Hiss Case: The FBI, Congress, and the Cold War. Correspondence, notes, research materials and working drafts are included.
    Materials added to this subseries in 2016 largely relate to the 1996 release of the Venona papers. They contain clippings, articles, photocopies of the Venona papers, handwritten notes, drafts written by Navasky and others. Other research materials related to the Hiss case including copies of the FBI file of Victor Perlo, and published works about Hiss by John Lowenthal and Tony Hiss. These materials also include correspondence with Tony Hiss related to the creation of the website Algerhiss.com.
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss", Apr 8, 1978 (Box 72, Folder 7)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "British Reviews" of Perjury: The Hiss-Chambers Case, 1978 (Box 72, Folder 8)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Correspondence Hiss Issue" Post-article (includes letters from Malcolm Cowley, John Henry Faulk, Eliot Janeway, Anthony Lewis, and Albert Moltz. Also copy of letter from Kurt Vonnegut), 1978 (Box 72, Folder 9)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Chambers in CP" (HUAC hearing transcript pages-Whittaker Chambers Testimony), 1948 (Box 72, Folder 10)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Eddy, George", 1976, 1978 (Box 72, Folder 11)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Eisler", Gerhart, undated (Box 72, Folder 12)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": Field, Hermann, 1978, undated (Box 72, Folder 13)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Garlin, Sender", 1978, undated (Box 72, Folder 14)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Herbst, Josephine", 1949, 1978 (Box 72, Folder 15)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Hiss, Alger", 1957, 1975, 1978 (Box 72, Folder 16)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": Hiss, Alger "Pre-Perjury articles and clips" (includes copy of Richard M. Nixon speech "The Hiss Case"), 1950, 1972-1978, undated (Box 72, Folder 17)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Hiss, Donald", 1951, 1978 (Box 72, Folder 18)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Hiss, Priscilla", 1978, undated (Box 72, Folder 19)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Hiss, Tony", 1973, 1977, undated (Box 72, Folder 20)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Kaplan, Karel", 1977-1978, 1980, undated (Box 72, Folder 21)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Krieger, Sam", 1978 (Box 72, Folder 22)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Krieger, Sam" - Sam Krieger v. Allen Weinstein et al. (includes transcript of Krieger interview by Weinstein), 1978-1980 (Box 72, Folder 23)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Krieger, Sam" - Sam Krieger v. Allen Weinstein et al. (deposition of Allen Weinstein), 1979 (Box 72, Folder 24)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Lieber, Maxim", 1976-1978 (Box 72, Folder 25)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Licht", 1949 (Box 72, Folder 26)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Lowenthal, John", 1976-1980 (Box 72, Folder 27)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Massing, Hede", 1978 (Box 72, Folder 28)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Nation (and New Republic) articles on Perjury", 1978-1979 (Box 72, Folder 29)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Navasky Drafts", 1978 (Box 72, Folder 30)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Nobile, Philip", 1976, 1978 (Box 72, Folder 31)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": Notes, 1978 (Box 72, Folder 32)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Perlo, Victor", 1949 (Box 72, Folder 33)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Peter, Josef", circa 1949, 1978 (Box 72, Folder 34)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": Post-article Press, 1978-1980, undated (Box 72, Folder 35)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Reuben, Bill" (William A. Reuben), 1975, 1978 (Box 72, Folder 36)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Reuben, Bill" (William A. Reuben), undated (Box 72, Folder 37)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": Reviews of Perjury, 1978, undated (Box 72, Folder 38)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Robinson-Reuben Case", 1979, undated (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Robinson-Reuben Case" - FOIA responses, Department of State, 1930s, 1976-1978 (Box 73, Folder 2)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Rosenward, Harold", 1975, 1978 (Box 73, Folder 3)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Smith, John Chabot", 1976, 1978 (Box 73, Folder 4)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Typewriter", 1949, 1976, undated (Box 73, Folder 5)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Waltuch, Jack", 1978 (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Weinstein Articles, etc." (includes paper "The Alger Hiss Case: An Assessment"), 1969-1979, undated (Box 73, Folder 7)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Weinstein-Navasky Correspondence", 1978 (Box 73, Folder 8)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Whitman, Alden", 1978 (Box 73, Folder 9)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Willert, Paul", 1978 (Box 73, Folder 10)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Winter, Ella", 1978 (Box 73, Folder 11)
    - "The Case Not Proved Against Alger Hiss": "Wyzanski, Judge Charles E.", 1978 (Box 73, Folder 12)
    - "Ideology and Truth: Some Notes on the Hiss Case, The Cold War, Historiography and Imagery" (discusses writing of "The Case Not Proved..."), undated (Box 73, Folder 13)
    - Various Navasky Articles re: Alger Hiss, 1977, 1978, 1997-1999 (Box 73, Folder 14)
    - "Weinstein, Hiss, and the Transformation of Historical Ambiguity Into Cold War Verity": Correspondence, 1981 (Box 73, Folder 15)
    - "Weinstein, Hiss, and The Transformation of Historical Ambiguity into Cold War Verity": Notes, undated (Box 73, Folder 16)
    - "Weinstein, Hiss, and The Transformation of Historical Ambiguity into Cold War Verity": Research materials (includes copy of motion for summary judgment, "Alger Hiss and William A Reuben v. The Department of Justice et al.", 1981, undated (Box 73, Folder 17)
    - "Weinstein, Hiss, and The Transformation of Historical Ambiguity into Cold War Verity": Working drafts, undated (Box 73, Folder 18)
    - Alger Hiss: Articles and Clippings, 1990-1992 (Box 103, Box 104)
    - Alger Hiss: Venona Papers Notes and Photocopies, 1995-1996 (Box 104, Box 105, Box 108)
    - Alger Hiss: General Research, 1990-2009 (Box 105, Box 106, Box 107)
    - Alger Hiss: Victor Perlo FBI File, 1949-1972 (Box 106)
    - Alger Hiss Alger Hiss Project: Organizational Planning, 2003-2006 (Box 107)
  - Subseries VIID: Plays
    Although the collection contains a few examples of Navasky's early plays, most of the material in this subseries relates to Starr's Last Tape, a one-act play written by Navasky and his friend Richard Lingeman. Inspired by Kenneth Starr's investigation of Bill Clinton and Samuel Beckett's Krapp's Last Tape, it had a run at the Berkshire Film Festival in September of 1999. The collection contains correspondence, drafts and notes, research (including a complete copy of The Starr Report with the White House response), and reviews of the play.
    - Bech v. Jarndyce proposal for a television series, 2005 (Box 73, Folder 19)
    - Early interest in playwriting, 1954-1955 (Box 73, Folder 20)
    - An Emory Mack Adventure "Operation Statehood", undated (Box 73, Folder 21)
    - Emory Mack Breaks the Ice, undated (Box 73, Folder 22)
    - The Shopping Hour, circa 1954 (Box 73, Folder 23)
    - Starr's Last Tape, 1999 (Box 73, Folder 24)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Correspondence (also includes some script drafts), 1998-1999 (Box 73, Folder 25)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Drafts (early) with notes and insertions, Jul 1998-Aug 1998 (Box 73, Folder 26)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Drafts (with annotations), 1998 (Box 73, Folder 27)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Drafts and notes, with Starr biographical information and "Christian Life in the Law" by Kenneth Starr, 1995, 1996, 1998 (Box 73, Folder 28)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Drafts and notes with annotations, 1998 (Box 73, Folder 29)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Notes, undated (Box 73, Folder 30)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Performance and reviews, 1999 (Box 73, Folder 31)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Research/background, 1992-1998 (Box 74, Folder 1)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Research/background, 1998-1999, undated (Box 74, Folder 2)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Research/background - magazine issues, 1998-1999 (Box 74, Folder 3)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Research/background - newspaper clippings, 1997-1998 (Box 74, Folder 4)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Research/background - newspaper clippings, 1998-1999, undated (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Research/background - newspaper sections, Sep 13, 1998 (Box 74, Folder 6)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Research/background - newspaper sections, Sep 22, 1998 (Box 74, Folder 7)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Research/background - newspaper sections, Feb 13, 1999 (Box 74, Folder 8)
    - Starr's Last Tape: Research/background - The Starr Report (complete text and White House response), 1998 (Box 74, Folder 9)
    - We Held These Truths or United We Stand, circa 1952 (Box 74, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 74, Folder 11)
  - Subseries VIIE: Speeches
    Folders in the "Speeches" subseries contain a variety of materials: some hold completed speech texts, drafts, or fragments; others contain items related to a speech but with none of the speech text. Not all the speeches are identified and some folders reflect Navasky appearances where he did not give a talk or speech but may have participated in a panel or question and answer session. The folders that are arranged chronologically and labeled "Speeches" reflect original order and titles.
    - Speeches, 1999-2015 (Box 95)
    - "100 Years of Clifford Odets-Celebration": Panel participation, 2006 (Box 74, Folder 12)
    - Appearances (copies of speeches/talks not included), 1973-2007 (Box 74, Folder 13)
    - Boston Public Library "Democracy and the Press..." (emails), 2005, 2006 (Box 74, Folder 14)
    - Canadian Magazine Association keynote speech, 2005-2006 (Box 74, Folder 15)
    - "The Case for the Partisan Press" research, press and related email (copy of speech not included), 2005-2006 (Box 74, Folder 16)
    - "The Case for Unbalanced Journalism" research and notes, 1994, undated (Box 74, Folder 17)
    - "Citizen Journalism" speech, draft and research, 2009 (Box 74, Folder 18)
    - Commencement speech, CUNY Graduate Center (draft), May 25, 2006 (Box 74, Folder 19)
    - "Did Venona Make a Difference?" Remarks at Venona Conference, National War College, Oct 4, 1996 (Box 74, Folder 20)
    - Harry Walker, Inc. (Agent for Navasky speaking engagements): Contract (1972-1974) and related materials, 1971-1972 (Box 74, Folder 21)
    - Introductions, 2005, 2010 (Box 74, Folder 22)
    - "Is the Press Too Liberal?" research and notes, 1992-1996, undated (Box 74, Folder 23)
    - JASA West Side Senior Center material (May 21, 2006 appearance; copy of speech not included), 2005-2006 (Box 74, Folder 24)
    - Keynote speech at Tamiment Library's Conference on Alger Hiss and History, 2007 (Box 74, Folder 25)
    - "McCarthyism and Journalism" drafts, 2006 (Box 74, Folder 26)
    - "The Nation and the Historical Role of the Journal of Opinion" (transcript of session at The New School including Q and A), 1997 (Box 74, Folder 27)
    - Radio, 1996, 1997 (Box 74, Folder 28)
    - Speeches, 1981-1988 (Box 74, Folder 29)
    - Speeches, 1990-1996 (Box 74, Folder 30)
    - Speeches, 1998-2000 (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - Speeches, 2001-2003 (Box 75, Folder 2)
    - Speeches, 2004-2005 (Box 75, Folder 3)
    - Speeches, 2009 (Box 75, Folder 4)
    - Speeches, undated (Box 75, Folder 5)
    - Speeches (includes drafts and fragments), undated (Box 75, Folder 6)
    - "Synagogue Speech", 2006 (Box 75, Folder 7)
    - Talk at Westport, CT Public Library (includes draft, notes, press and associated emails), 2005-2006 (Box 75, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified speech (draft) with flagged and annotated copy of A Matter of Opinion used in speech, undated (Box 75, Folder 9)
- Series VIII: Navasky at Columbia University, 1963-2015
  - Subseries VIIIA: Columbia Graduate School of Journalism
    This subseries contains Navasky materials relating to Columbia University's Graduate School of Journalism, where he directs the George Delacorte Center for Magazine Journalism. Highlights include a series of lectures by editors, writers, art directors, and publishers from magazines such as Vanity Fair, The New Yorker, and Harper's. The lectures, delivered as part of the George Delacorte Lecture Series, became chapters in The Art of Making Magazines, edited by Navasky and Evan Cornog (Dean of the School of Communication at Hofstra University and former publisher of the Columbia Journalism Review).
    There are also materials associated with Navasky's Magazine Workshop in which students create and publish a complete magazine from scratch. Titled The New York Review of Magazines, it is a magazine about magazines. Workshop materials and full issues are contained in this subseries.